我先问你一件事
Let me ask you something first
你上一次换手机
The last time you got a new phone
花了多少钱
How much did you spend
还是12000
Or 12000
你有没有想过
Have you ever wondered
10年前最贵的iPhone才5288
10 years ago the most expensive iPhone was only 5288
现在ProMax1TB
Now a ProMax 1TB
价格翻了快3倍
The price nearly tripled
但你这10年
But in these 10 years
工资涨了几倍
How many times has your salary gone up
更怪的是
What's even weirder
越贵
The more expensive
越多人抢
The more people fight for it
苹果2024年财报
Apple's 2024 financial report
iPhone卖出23亿台
iPhone sold 230 million units
Pro系列占一半以上
Pro series accounted for over half
你是不是也这样过
Have you been like this too
预算本来8000
Your budget was 8000 to begin with
到了店里咬咬牙加2000买Pro
Then at the store you grit your teeth and added 2000 for the Pro
反正都买了
Might as well go all in
这不是你一个人
You're not the only one
真相是
The truth is
一部手机为什么越来越贵
Why phones keep getting more expensive
跟成本几乎没关系
Has almost nothing to do with cost
跟你的脑子有关系
It has everything to do with your brain
今天我用10分钟
Today I'll use 10 minutes
告诉你手机变贵背后的3个经济学陷阱
To tell you about the 3 economic traps behind rising phone prices
搞懂它
Understand them
你下次买手机至少能少花3000块
And you'll save at least 3000 on your next phone
而且这3个陷阱
And these 3 traps
不只在手机店
Aren't just at the phone store
你买车
When you buy a car
买包
Buy a bag
买电脑
Buy a computer
报培训班
Sign up for a training course
全在踩
You're falling for all of them
你想想这个画面
Picture this scene
你坐地铁
You're on the subway
对面那个人掏出一台折叠的MateXT
The person across from you pulls out a foldable MateXT
你5000块的iPhone拿手里
And your 5000-yuan iPhone in hand
都觉得有点寒酸
Suddenly feels a bit embarrassing
注意听
Pay attention
这种感觉不是你矫情
This feeling isn't you being overly sensitive
是经济学家研究了100多年的一个规律
It's a pattern economists have studied for over 100 years
1899年
In 1899
美国经济学家凡勃伦写了一本书
American economist Veblen wrote a book
叫有闲阶级论
Called The Theory of the Leisure Class
他发现一个反常识的现象
He discovered a counterintuitive phenomenon
有些东西
Some things
价格越贵
The higher the price
买的人反而越多
The more people want to buy them
按经济学常识
According to basic economics
一个商品涨价10%
When a product's price goes up 10%
需求至少跌5%
Demand should drop at least 5%
但有些东西反过来
But some things work the other way
涨价30%
Price goes up 30%
销量涨50%
Sales go up 50%
这后来被叫做凡勃伦效应
This later became known as the Veblen effect
劳力士
Rolex
爱马仕
Hermes
奔驰大G
Mercedes G-Wagon
都是这一类
All fall into this category
你猜苹果是不是
Guess if Apple is one too
是
It is
从乔布斯起就是
Since Jobs it's always been
2007年第一代iPhone卖499美元
In 2007 the first iPhone sold for 499 dollars
当时诺基亚最贵的型号也就300美元
Back then Nokia's most expensive model was only 300 dollars
苹果一上来就把自己定在一个高出别人一档的位置
Apple positioned itself a full tier above everyone else right from the start
之后每一代都涨
Every generation after that went up
iPhone4卖4999
iPhone 4 sold for 4999
iPhone8卖5888
iPhone 8 sold for 5888
iPhone12卖6299
iPhone 12 sold for 6299
iPhone15ProMax卖12999
iPhone 15 ProMax sold for 12999
价格曲线一路向上
The price curve just keeps climbing
销量也一路向上
And sales keep climbing too
为什么
Why
因为对一部分人来说
Because for some people
手机已经不是手机了
A phone is no longer just a phone
是身份
It's status
是品味
It's taste
是我跟别人不一样的那张标签
It's the label that says I'm different from everyone else
凡勃伦自己说过一句话
Veblen himself once said
消费某些商品真正的目的
The real purpose of consuming certain goods
是炫耀有能力消费它们
Is to show off the ability to afford them
苹果太懂这个了
Apple understands this perfectly
他们卖的不是性能
They're not selling performance
是我配得上的感觉
They're selling the feeling that I deserve this
你回想一下
Think back
你上次咬牙买Pro的那一秒
The second you grit your teeth and bought the Pro
真的是因为120赫兹屏幕吗
Was it really because of the 120Hz screen
还是只是不想拿那部看上去就便宜的标准版
Or did you just not want to be seen with the cheap-looking standard model
请你诚实回答自己
Be honest with yourself
我再给你一个更狠的数据
Let me give you an even more brutal stat
茅台2024年涨价8%
Maotai raised prices 8% in 2024
销量同比涨14%
Sales jumped 14% year over year
爱马仕铂金包2025年涨价12%
Hermes Birkin bag went up 12% in 2025
预约排到2027年
The waitlist extends to 2027
这些品牌的财务报表里
Hidden in these brands' financial reports
藏着同一个逻辑
Is the exact same logic
涨价不是为了多赚一点钱
Raising prices isn't about making a bit more money
是为了筛掉不够格的客户
It's about filtering out customers who don't qualify
筛掉之后
Once filtered out
剩下的客户更愿意为我跟别人不一样买单
The remaining customers are more willing to pay for being different
苹果在手机行业里
In the phone industry Apple
干的就是同一件事
Is doing the exact same thing
每一次涨价
Every price increase
都是一次身份门槛的拉高
Is raising the status barrier another notch
你以为它在涨价
You think they're raising prices
其实它在筛选谁配做苹果用户
They're actually screening who deserves to be an Apple user
注意听
Listen up
这里讲一个比凡勃伦效应更狠的招
Here's a trick even more ruthless than the Veblen effect
它叫价格锚定
It's called price anchoring
你去苹果店
You walk into an Apple store
店员第一句话从来不会推标准版
The staff will never lead with the standard model
他会先拉你去看ProMax
They'll pull you over to look at the ProMax first
咱们这是顶配
This is our top model
1TB
钛合金边框
Titanium frame
你一听
You hear that
好贵
So expensive
然后他指向旁边
Then they point to the side
这是Pro
This is the Pro
512G
你心里一比
You compare in your head
便宜了2500
2500 cheaper